Today's דף daf is ע"א, ayin aleph, 71, and we pick up
at the bottom of ע"א עמוד ב' ayin amud bet at the
two dots, which is about ten lines from the bottom where the
גמרא Gemara says גופא, gufa, starts with an asterisk. גופא. gufa. So,
let's go back to something we quoted earlier. We're in the middle
of a whole discussion about a man making a vow that his
wife can't get benefit from him, and how that will lead to
us, if it goes beyond a certain period of time, demanding they
get divorced, and since he's the one that made the vow, that
she would get the כתובה. ketuvah.
So now the גמרא Gemara quotes and then how does he solve
it in the interim and have a third party provide for her
in a way in which he's not directly, explicitly directing that third
party,
commanding, instructing the third party directly, and then it's not seen as
if it's coming from him. So now we're going to quote related
cases. גופא, gufa, let's look back at what we quoted earlier in
the משנה בנדרים. Mishnah in Nedarim.
המודר הנאה מחבירו, Hamudar hana'ah me-chavero, somebody is in a state where
they are forbidden to get הנאה hana'ah because of a vow from
their friend. ואין לו מה יאכל, V'ein lo mah yochal, but this
guy, who took this vow in spite or he was so angry
with his friend, he's now starving today. He has nothing to eat.
Okay. יילך אצל חנווני הרגיל אצלו, Yalech eitzel hanvani ha-ragil etzlo,
so the person who has the food to provide, he goes to
the מכולת makolet guy, the bodega guy, who he's accustomed to, who
knows him, ואומר לו, v'omer lo, and says to him, איש פלוני
מודר הנאה ממני, ish ploni mudar hana'ah mimeni, ראובן Reuven over there,
he took a vow, he's not allowed to get benefit from me.
But he has nothing to eat. ואיני יודע מה אעשה לו, V'eini
yode'a mah e'eseh lo, I don't know what I can do for
him. My hands are tied. So the guy, the bodega guy, picks
up on the hint, והוא נותן לו, v'hu notein lo, and he
goes ahead and gives ראובן Reuven some eggs and bread and milk
and provides for him. ובא ונוטל מזה, U'va v'notel mi-zeh, and he
comes back to the first guy and he says, you know, I
gave all this stuff to ראובן. Reuven. He says, oh, that's so
nice. Here, let me give you 20 bucks, let me give you
40 bucks. So it's not explicit, but it's obviously very clear what
somebody wants done. Okay.
Now, ביתו לבנות וגדירו לגדור ושדהו לקצור, beito livnot v'gidero ligdor v'sadehu
liktzor, where
let's say it's not that the guy ממש mamash has nothing to
eat, but still, like I feel very magnanimous and I want to
help this guy, and his house is falling down, he needs his
house built, he needs a fence to be made, or his wall
to be built, or somebody needs to harvest his field, and he
has nobody to do it for him, and I have the means
and I'd like to, but he took this vow. הולך אצל פועלים
הרגילים אצלו, Holech eitzel po'alim haragilin etzlo, I go to some workers
who I'm accustomed to hiring, ואומר להן, v'omer lahen, and I say
to them, איש פלוני מודר הנאה ממני, ish ploni mudar hana'ah mimeni,
ראובן Reuven took a vow, he can't get benefit from me, ואיני
יודע מה לעשות לו, v'eini yode'a mah la'asot lo, I don't know
what I can do for him because he has all these things
that need to get done, but my hands are tied. הן עושין
עמו, Hein osim imo, so they go and they do the work
for him, ובאין ונוטלין שכרן מזה, u'va'in v'notlin scharan mi-zeh, and they
come back to me and they get their pay. Now, the interesting
thing is that the language of נוטלין שכרן notlin scharan or נוטל
notel sounds like they can actually, like, demand it from me. You
know, presumably if they come to court and I change my mind,
presumably they can't actually press that as a case in court or
else it really would be like I had hired them. But clearly,
that's the sort of within the game that we're playing, they'll tell
me how much it is and then I'll decide to give them
a nice gift. Okay.
היו מהלכין בדרך, Hayu mahlachin baderech,
now, here I am going with ראובן Reuven and we're taking a
journey, ואין עמו מה
יאכל, v'ein imo mah yochal, and ראובן Reuven brought no food, and
I have food on me. So now we're stuck. We don't have
any third parties, right? So, we're just the two of us. נותן
לאחר לשום מתנה, Notein l'acher l'shum matanah, so let's say hopefully I
can find a third
party, let me give you this gift, והלה נוטל ואוכל, v'halaz notel
v'ochal,
and then ראובן Reuven goes to this third party and says, oh,
I see you have some food, would you mind, could I share
some of it? So if you can find a third party and
can clue him in, then you go ahead and do that. ומותר,
U'mutar, it's allowed. אם אין שם אחר, Im ein sham acher, now
there's no third party, now I'm really stuck. מניח על גבי הסלע,
Mani'ach al gabei haselah, I put it on a rock, או על
גבי הגדר, o gabei agedair, or wall, ואומר, v'omer, and I say,
הרי הן
מופקרין לכל מי שיחפוץ, harei hein mufkarim l'chol mi sheyachpotz, so I'm
with ראובן, Reuven, there's nobody in a radius of 10 miles, and
I put it on a rock, anybody who wants can go and
take it, it's הפקר hefker for anybody. So the only one around
is ראובן, Reuven, and he comes and takes it. והלה נוטל ואוכל
ומותר, V'halaz notel v'ochal u'mutar, and that's permissible. So even if there's
no third party, we can make it work. רבי יוסי אוסר, Rabbi
Yose oser, Rabbi Yose forbids this last case. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר רבה מאי טעמא דרבי יוסי, amar Rabbah, mai ta'ama d'Rabbi
Yose, what's the reason of Rabbi Yose? גזירה משום מעשה דבית חורון,
Gzeirah mishum ma'aseh d'Beit Choron, top of ע"א עמוד א', ayin aleph
amud aleph, a גזירה gzeirah because of the story of בית חורון,
Beit Choron, which was a place, which is a משנה Mishnah in
נדרים. Nedarim. from his father or no his father couldn't get any
הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah* from him I think the case was and then
he was marrying off his son and he wanted his father to
come to the סעודה *Seudah* so what did he do he gave
all of the food of the סעודה *Seudah* to a third party
and said you know so that this guy is here these this
is all of this food is yours because that will enable my
father to come to the meal so the guy you know to
the wedding feast so the guy said oh all the food is
mine great I'm going to be מקדיש makdish *makdish* it so he
made it he said it as a point to basically say don't
try to use me to get around your נדר neder. *Neder* if
you like it's sort of like the whole thing we discussed through
פסח Pesach, *Pesach* how much did we really sell it to the
non-Jew if you really give it to me and that really allows
you to get out of it to avoid the vow then I'm
entitled to go ahead and to sanctify it so because of those
types of concerns that at a certain point it becomes a farce
that seems to be the point of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here
it's not a concern that somebody's going to be מקדיש *makdish* it
there's nobody around to be מקדיש *makdish* it but the point is
that at a certain point it becomes so much of a farce
so transparent what's happening that we really can't allow it so that
really is the debate here where there's no third party yes
so is that the reason why we force the
I'm listening, yeah
גירושין *Gerushin* in the thirty days? No the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
that we'll get to that גמרא Gemara *Gemara* yes but I mean
why can't he just have them you know put it on a
mat let his wife take it?
Yeah but we don't force the divorce because there's no solution there
is a solution of the third party right the only problem is
that we that we don't think that the marriage is tenable beyond
a certain point not that the guy can't actually you know just
practically be provided for right so the reason the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says the thirty days is beyond that it either becomes a public
matter
or it is true by the way no one of the answers
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* gave was that beyond thirty days we can't
trust the guy to continue to do it so תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*
asks the question well what about some of these other solutions why
wouldn't they work so תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* gives reasons why we can't
rely on them but it seems that the more much more the
reason as the other cases in the משנה Mishna. *Mishna* show is
not because we think she won't be provided for we can't find
some practical solution but it's just because the marriage with that type
of a נדר neder *Neder* between them is not you know a
viable marriage it's a
strange name for these people making these types of נדרים nedarim *Nedarim*
it's like a strange way of go I can't get any benefit
right so you're right I mean it's an interesting point because classically
the vows in the תורה Torah *Torah* I mean the whole idea
of vows is very foreign to us actually interestingly within סדר נשים
*Seder Nashim* is נדרים nedarim. *Nedarim* and we're going to get to
that מסכת *Masechet* soon enough but it's very foreign to us but
what it would actually do is allow people to almost structure a
more personal religious life if you would like now we have an
idea of people take חומרות *chumrot* you look for more
opportunities to bring more religiosity into your life so nowadays it expresses
itself by people taking חומרות *chumrot* there the way you took חומרות
*chumrot* was not like פסקנינג *paskening* that חלב ישראל Yisrael *chalav Yisrael*
is you have to drink חלב ישראל *chalav Yisrael* but it was
like taking a vow so I feel like I want to deny
myself certain things maybe it's an ascetic type of a thing so
I'm going to forbid certain things on me and so on so
that seems like the primary thing it was and that's why the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* compares taking vows to like building a במה *Bamah*
building a private altar you're sort of like making your own tailor-made
sort of religious experience but what you see by these cases is
that then how it gets
abused once you have that power to make things forbidden then it
can be used in ways of like
spite interpersonal like oh to heck with you blah blah blah or
like to and it becomes a barrier between people which is like
a fascinating point because that's also sometimes the types of חומרות *chumrot*
that people adopt often are ones that sort of say we don't
eat in certain people's homes we don't do certain things they also
sometimes become barriers but
it doesn't seem like vows were ever in principle intended to be
used to create as forbidding you against me and creating this wall
between us it seems like that was one thing that derived from
it once it became a phenomenon but that's a good point to
sort of bring that out that that's not the primary aspect of
what a vow
is
from the idea of גזירה משום מעשה דבית חורון *Gezeira mishum ma'aseh
de-Beit Choron* it doesn't sound like רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi *Rabbi Yose*
is concerned that this is not a real gift that's not his
problem it's that he doesn't want this to happen this way well
but then he wouldn't allow the earlier cases about using a third
well I guess it's I was assuming I think that it's pretty
clear that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yose* אוסר *oser* is only
on the last case not on all the earlier cases with a
third party so it's not actually the case of בית חורון Beis
Choron, *Beit Choron* because בית חורון *Beit Choron* needed a third party
to say fine I'm going to sanctify it or whatever but what
was at the core of the problem of the story of בית
חורון *Beit Choron* was that if it's such a if it's so
transparent and such a farce then you can't use that device so
the way I understood it was that the case of הפקר *hefker*
bordered on something being
clearly farcical that's the way I understood
it but The גמרא Gemara actually says that's right, that's actually what
the גמרא Gemara says, that either he did lose his money or
if the guy didn't have the power to be מקדיש it then
it wasn't a way to get around the נדר. neder Right.
Exactly. So if רבי יוסי Rebi Yosi was sort of saying it
by the earlier case, it were the two of, it's like, you
know, the two of us walking in the desert and I'm giving
it to a third party, that's more comparable to the בית חורון,
but it seems like his emphasis is really the last case, which
is basically the one that is the, you know, the most of
a הערמה, ha'arama, of a, you know, deceit type of thing. Okay.
So רבי יהודה אומר מישראל חודש אחד. Rebbi Yehuda Omer mi'Yisrael chodesh
echad. So רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda distinguishes between for a case of
a marriage to a non-כהן, Kohein, we let them, we tolerate this
vow forbidding benefit for a month, for a case of a כהן
Kohein which is an irreversible if they get divorced we tolerate it
for two months. So the גמרא Gemara says, first it starts with
the issue about when he says one month for a non-כהן. Kohein.
היינו תנא קמא, Hainu Tanna Kamma, that's the same position of the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who said thirty days. So אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye, כהנת אתא לאשמועינן, Kohenes ata le'ashmi'einan, and this comes to tell
us about the wife of a כהן. Kohein. You're right, the first
case was saying ישראל was redundant, his חידוש chiddish was to speak
about the wife of a כהן. Kohein. רבא אמר, Rava amar, now
רבא Rava says you know what there is even a difference even
regarding to this idea of the month. חודש מלא וחודש חסר איכא
בינייהו. Chodesh malei ve-chodesh chaser ika beinaihu. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
says thirty days and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says a month. So
a month isn't necessarily thirty days, a month could be twenty-nine days.
Now תוספות Tosafos has a little bit a question, does that mean
that a month always means twenty-nine days or does he mean that
you go by the calendar? So, you know, if it's, some months
would be twenty-nine days, some months thirty days, but it's not a
fixed thirty days like the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says. Okay, now
we get to something that's more of our focus.
אמר רב לא שנו אלא במפרש. Amar Rav lo shanu ella bi-mefaresh.
This idea that you get a month, you know, that we will
tolerate it for a month, is if you explicitly say, the husband
explicitly says, you know, my benefit is forbidden to my wife for
a month. So anytime he says fifteen days, twenty days, up to
a month, we allow it. If he says for, you know, thirty-one
days, then we say go ahead and get divorced, and we would
say that right away because the נדר neder is for more, it's
for more than a month. So this issue, what is the length
of the period, is a question of what is the length of
the vow? We'll allow for a נדר neder up to that's that's
that's said to that has a a date of thirty days, up
to thirty days, a נדר neder that's a period is longer then
we're going to demand a divorce.
Doesn't this mean if he doesn't specify it at all it's also
not valid?
Yeah, if he doesn't specify it at all then it's forever, then
certainly. Right. Okay, but the point is that we will, we will
make our decision today about whether we're going, right, and we're going
to determine how long is the נדר neder for. If it's not
if it's not that long we'll allow it, if it's too long
we're going to demand a divorce today. That's how רב Rav reads
the משנה. Mishna Okay. ושמואל אמר אפילו בסתם לא יוציא. U'Shmuel amar
afilu bi'stam lo yotzi. Now שמואל Shmuel says
even if he says no no time limit, he says you know
forever, or without saying a time limit it's like he said forever,
you know, my הנאה hanaah is forbidden to my wife, then the
question of a month or more is not a question of how
long the נדר neder was made for but how long we will
wait with that נדר neder. in place. So what's the point of
us waiting a month if he said a נדר neder forever, what
good is it going to do to wait a month? So שמואל
Shmuel will tell you the following thing, he'll tell you this. ושמואל
אמר אפילו בסתם לא יוציא, U'Shmuel amar afilu bi'stam lo yotzi, even
if it's סתם stam we're going to make we're going to wait
a month before demanding the divorce. So what's going to be accomplished
then? שמא ימצא פתח לנדרו, Shema yimtza pesach le'nidro, because if we
give him a month there's a way out of vows, you can
go to a חכם chacham and you can do a היתר heter
for your נדרים Nedarim if you find a פתח, pesach, an opening,
oh had I thought about this I never would have made my
נדר. neder So as opposed to the sort of the, you know,
the התרת נדרים hataras nedarim that we do on ערב ראש השנה
Erev Rosh Hashanah where it's all very pro forma, when vows were
a real thing the התרת נדרים hataras nedarim could not be taken
for granted. You needed actually a legitimate reason, you know, a legitimate
basis for releasing somebody of their נדרים. Nedarim But it was a
possibility. So therefore שמואל Shmuel says even if it's a נדר neder
for forever, the משנה Mishna. doesn't mean how long was the נדר
neder made for, it means once you have this נדר neder in
place how long do we wait? We will wait up to a
month to see if you can find some way out of it.
If it's taken you more than a month then we're going to
get get you divorced at that stage. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says והאיפלגו בה חדא זימנא, Ve'ha-ifligu bei chada zimna, now
why do you have to argue that in terms of our case
of the husband taking a נדר of the wife deriving benefit whether
it's סתם stam or במפרש? bi-mefaresh? They debated it in another case,
in an earlier משנה. Mishna, דתנן, De-tnan, we learned in an earlier
משנה, mishnah, המדיר אשתו מתשמיש המטה, Hamadir ishto mi-tashmish hamitah,
a man basically prevent, you know, made a נדר that his wife
can't have sex with him. Now again how does he do that
if he's obligated to have sex with his wife? So it's not
that he forbids his sexual pleasure on his wife, she has rights
to to derive sexual pleasure from him. It's the opposite. He forbids
his wife's sexual pleasure on him. So he's not directly
undercutting, you know, he's
not
directly undercutting his obligation, indirectly he's undercutting his obligation but not directly.
מחלוקת, machloket,
that's when you explicitly said, the man said for one week her
sex with her will be forbidden to me or for two weeks,
that's what you explicitly said, and then we'll decide right now, are
we going to allow the vow or are we going to sort
of be okay with it or are we going to demand a
divorce? But בסתם, b'stam, if he said without explaining how long, and
therefore it means indefinitely,
יוציא לאלתר, yotzi l'alter, then we demand an immediate divorce because clearly
it's indefinite and therefore the marriage can't be sustained with this vow,
so get a divorce.
That's רב, Rav, and שמואל Shmuel says, אפילו בסתם נמי לא יוציא.
afilu b'stam nami lo yotzi. No,
even if the vow is indefinite, he doesn't get divorced right away,
the duration of one week or two weeks is not the duration
that the vow was made for but how long we wait to
see if you'll resolve it. שמא ימצא פתח לנדרו, shema yimtza petach
l'nidro, we would wait a week or two to see if he
can find a way to get himself released from his vow.
I see what you mean, a week or two, not indefinite.
No, the duration in the משנה, mishnah one week or two weeks,
is not a question of how long the vow was made for
but how long we wait with the vow in place.
So שמואל Shmuel means one or two
weeks in that case
for that period. So in the case of the sex it was
one or two weeks, in the case of the מזונות mezonot it
was one month or two months for a כהן. kohen. So the
גמרא Gemara, says, yeah. The גמרא Gemara says, צריכא. tzricha. No, you
need to have their argument in both cases. דאי אתמר בהא, di'itmar
b'ha, if you had said the case by sex,
בהא קאמר רב, b'ha ka'amar Rav, that would be where רב Rav
says that if it's indefinite, you've got to get to a divorce
immediately. We won't tolerate, we won't give you time to see if
you can find
the פתח. petach. בהא קאמר רב משום דלא אפשר בפרנס b'ha ka'amar
Rav mishum d'lo efshar b'parnas because, you know what? There's no third
party that can provide that for the woman. Okay? So therefore
every day is a problem there. So there we won't tolerate any
waiting of time.
Does it make a difference if they can't actually have sex anyway?
Yeah, I mean whatever, we sort of have to have some general
rules in place but maybe in theory you could have. אבל בהא
דאפשר בפרנס, aval b'ha d'efshar b'parnas, in our case, maybe we're more
prepared to adopt a שמואל Shmuel approach of let's wait and see
if you can find a way out of it because in the
interim somebody else can be providing the food. So maybe in that
case, אימא מודה ליה לשמואל, eima modeh lei l'Shmuel, maybe he'd agree
with שמואל, Shmuel, let's give the guy some time to see if
he can find a way out of it. ואי אתמר בהא, v'i
itmar b'ha, and had we just said the case about providing מזונות,
mezonot, בהא קאמר שמואל, b'ha ka'amar Shmuel, that's where שמואל Shmuel says
let's give it some time משום דאפשר בפרנס mishum d'efshar b'parnas because
again, same idea, you have somebody providing for her so we'd be
able to give a time. אבל בהיא, aval b'hi, in the case
of sex, אימא מודה ליה לרב, eima modeh lei l'Rav, maybe he
would agree with רב Rav that we can't, if the vow is
for too long,
we're not going to wait, every day we wait is going to
be a problem, so maybe he would agree with רב. Rav. צריכא,
tzricha, so it had to tell you that the argument in both
cases. Okay, but that's the debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel.
רב Rav says the duration is how explicitly long you've made the
vow for and we decide right away whether to allow it or
whether to say that this vow is a problem and therefore they
have to get divorced. And שמואל Shmuel says we're always going to
wait, no matter how long the vow is for, we're going to
give you a period of time to see if you can work
it out, to see if you can find a way to get
released from the vow. Yes.
Is it, the קשיא kashya is אידי ואידי בחדא זימנא, idi v'idi
b'chada zimna, right? The גמרא Gemara already taught that some other place.
That's a normal way to raise that type of objection, בחדא זימנא.
b'chada zimna.
Yeah,
I mean sometimes it can use different language like למה לי והא.
lama li v'ha. Yeah, is it similar to that? Yeah,
I mean I'd have to remind myself the
exact keywords that the גמרא Gemara, uses to frame it, but yes,
the גמרא Gemara often asks, for us it's like not a big
deal, like if you have this standing debate,
you're going to want to articulate it at every opportunity. But the
גמרא Gemara. is sort of saying well, we don't need to, we're
not stupid, we can apply it. So the reason you want to
articulate it at every opportunity is somebody shouldn't think that this case
might be different than the other case and might think that I
have a different opinion here. So we're going to explain why somebody
could have thought you would have had a different opinion here, why
you want to articulate it.
Yes. Is it true, you see the גמרא Gemara is using the
term חבר, chaver, חברו chavero just sort of loosely, just like the
חבורה, chaburah, like guys like
that?
No, I don't think it's technical here.
Okay, so now we're going to see how this debate plays out
in other
parts like how it would play out in the remaining of the
משניות mishnayot in our פרק. perek. So you will remember that or
whatever the second part of the משנה mishnah that we had. You
will remember that the second part of our משנה mishnah was a
case that the simple text to the משנה mishnah was that the
man said that his wife can't benefit from a certain type of
a fruit or his wife can't use a certain type of a
perfume. So the question was, let me first just explain before we
get to the גמרא, Gemara how can a man make his wife
forbidden to eat kumquats? Like he doesn't, if he said his kumquats
fine, but how could he make her forbidden to eat all kumquats?
How can he be the one? Because the משנה Mishnah says he
made his wife... the vow, how could he make the vow? So
there is a way. The way is indirect. Basically, what he could
say is, he could say,
"If you eat a- if you ever eat a kumquat, then, you
know, the הנאה hanaah of sex with me is forbidden on you,
or the הנאה of מזונות mezonos is forbidden on you." So you
don't actually directly make the kumquat forbidden by a vow. The man
isn't able. He makes it the condition by which there will be
a vow that he can make that will then come kick in
that will make the marriage intolerable. Okay, so effectively he through a
vow he effectively made it impossible for her to eat kumquats or
for her to use a certain type of a perfume. That would
be the way to explain the משנה Mishnah in the simple sense
that he is the one who is making the vow, he's imposing
it on her. We're going to see in a minute that the
גמרא Gemara because of this debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
feels that it's going to have to read the משנה Mishnah in
a different way. Although the משנה Mishnah. said he made the vow,
it's really going to say she made the vow. She said, "All
kumquats are forbidden to me," and his role was, was that he
didn't annul it. Okay, and that he actually he actually actively was
מקיים mekayem it or silently was מקיים mekayem it by not annulling
it during a day, he had a day to annul it and
he didn't. And therefore he in a way because of his active
or silent participation made the vow binding. And that's the other way
the גמרא's Gemara going to read the משנה. Mishnah, Well, then the
question is, why is that then a reason to get divorced, right?
So I might as well spell this out now. So in the
first scenario where he said sex is "my sex is forbidden to
you if you eat a kumquat," so then it seems like, okay,
you can't have a marriage like that because you always have this
threat that if she does this one thing that's off limits, you
know, like eating from the עץ הדעת, Etz Hadas, I guess, this
one thing that's off limits, then this vow is going to come
down and that's going to sort of, you know, make the marriage
intolerable. So you could say, well let's wait till that happens, but
maybe just dealing with that threat hanging over, that's not seen as
tolerable.
Okay, so we'll see about that in the גמרא, Gemara, but that
would at least be the idea why they would need to get
divorced. But if basically she said that the kumquats are forbidden and
I was מקיים mekayem it, maybe I shouldn't have been מקיים mekayem
it, I should have gotten her out of it, it wasn't a
nice thing. But how is a divorce going to help, right? What's
the divorce going to do? She still can't eat the kumquat. Exactly.
Exactly. So there's two answers in the ראשונים. Rishonim. תוספות Tosafos basically
says adding yet
another layer to the משנה, Mishnah that she basically said, "Kumquats are
forbidden to me as long as we're married." Okay. So therefore I
have to now so now, but that's bizarre also. What, we can't
tolerate a marriage when kumquats are off limit? Okay, so fine. So
okay, it's nice, get divorced, you want a
kumquat, get
a divorce, we'll free you to do that, but like why is
that so intolerable? So the ר"ן Ran basically says it's not about
the it's not, you know, it's not about the actual thing itself,
it's about the principle of the thing. That if he basically, you
know, sort of like you know, sort of affirmed this thing, made
this, was even silently participated in imposing this restriction on her, it
must mean, you know, that he doesn't care enough for her. That
he was willing to sort of now of course you could say,
"What do you mean honey, I was trying to help you out,
really you wanted to do that." Okay, but that's the way the
ר"ן Ran says it. That then it becomes this symbol of this,
like, distance between them and therefore that makes it sort of seem
like they can you know, the marriage can't go on because it's
this abiding symbol of the way that he sort of did not
express this care for her.
So in both of these and like, you know, "You know I
really want to watch my weight and I don't want to have
any..." Right. I mean, that's the okay, I understand.
That's the funny thing. Either of those are hard to explain. Okay,
clearly the simplest explanation simplest, there's no simplest explanation, but the simplest
explanation is taking the משנה Mishnah in
its simple sense, that he made the vow, in this indirect way:
"If you eat kumquats then sex will be forbidden." But he yeah,
right, about himself. Yeah, I mean, yes, "I can't get
sex then get the pleasure of sex from you," which effectively right,
which effectively makes the sex between them forbidden. So that's the simple
sense of the משנה Mishnah that he's the one making the vow,
although it's indirect, but he's making the vow. And then you also
understand why they have to get divorced. So that's clearly the best
way to read the משנה Mishnah as opposed to have her making
it, which is not the language of the משנה Mishnah. and makes
it harder to understand why they have to get divorced and what
benefit getting divorced will do. So now let's take a look at
the גמרא Gemara as it works through רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
in these two explanations.
הכי גרסינן, Hachi garsinan, right, he either actively did it or he
actively was מקיים mekayem it. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara תנן, Tnan, we taught our משנה. Mishnah, המדיר אשתו שלא
תטעום אחד מכל פירות, Hamadir ishto shelo titaam echad mikol peiros,
a person takes a vow, this is the literal sense of the
משנה, Mishnah that his wife can't get benefit from even one fruit,
one type of fruit. Okay, not one fruit but one type of
fruit. יוציא ויתן כתובה, Yotzi veyitein kesubah, he has to divorce her
and give the כתובה. kesubah. בשלמא לרב, Bishlama leRav, so now the
question is why here does it say divorce immediately, why doesn't it
say let's give it a month, right? That's the גמרא's Gemara question.
Why does the second part of the משנה Mishnah say immediate? It
should have said give it a month like it said before about
the
מזונות. mezonos. So בשלמא לרב, Bishlama l'Rav, here's the difference: כאן בסתמא
כאן במפורש. kan bistama kan bimfarash. When for רב Rav it's perfect.
When it says a month or two months, it's really was how
long was the duration of the vow for? So if the duration
of the vow was for a month, we'll tolerate it. More than
that we won't tolerate it. So this case, the duration was indefinite.
It's סתם, stam, so you gotta get divorced right away. That's exactly
what רב Rav says. That's the reason why there's no why it's
a right away because there was no duration said explicitly about the
vow.
כאן בסתמא כאן במפורש. kan bistama kan bimfarash. אלא לשמואל קשיא. Ella
l'Shmuel kashya. But for שמואל Shmuel both cases are סתם. stam. The
point of the משנה Mishnah was the vow was סתם, stam, but
we'll tolerate it for a month. So why here do we not
tolerate it for a month? So the גמרא Gemara says הכא במאי
עסקינן. hacha b'mai askinan. No,
here's what we're talking about in according to שמואל Shmuel and here's
where it switches it from him being the one to do it
to her being the one to do it. הכא במאי עסקינן hacha
b'mai askinan כשנדרה היא kshenadra hi וקיים לה איהו vekiyem la ihu
and he was מקיים mekayem it. He basically affirmed it and therefore
either actively or passively and therefore but through his through him the
vow is now binding. He had the he had an ability to
annul it and he didn't. Okay, וקסבר רבי מאיר vekasvar Rabbi Meir
and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds, cause we're assuming this סתם משנה
stam Mishnah is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, הוא נותן אצבע בין שיניה.
hu nosein etzba bein shineha. So okay, but if she made the
vow, why do they get divorced and he pays the כתובה? kesubah?
She's the one that made the vow, right? If we say she
made the vow. So no, cause this is the question, she made
the vow and he affirmed it, who do we say is to
blame? Okay, and the language it uses based on a language in
a משנה Mishnah, in נדרים is did he poke her in the
eye or did she poke herself in the eye? Okay, I say
poke in the eye, it says poke in the teeth. We just
got off from פסח, right? והקה את שיניו vehakei es shinav it
says to the רשע. rasha. Okay. So did he did he punch
her in the teeth or did she punch herself in the teeth?
Okay, so that's the question. So if he could have done it
and he didn't, we say he's to blame in the end or
he's at least enough to blame that he has to give the
כתובה. kesubah. Now the question is that the גמרא Gemara still didn't
answer the question about why here is it right away. Why here
don't we wait a month? Right? Okay, wonderful. She made the vow,
but why not still wait a month, right? What's the difference? So
there's a couple of explanations for that. רש"י Rashi basically says, and
I won't go into that right I'll just mention it now we'll
talk about it more because it'll be the גמרא Gemara later,
that if he's the one making the vow, we could say he
made the vow in a fit of anger and we're going to
give him time to cool off and to try to get out
of it. If she made a vow, then she's more then we
assume that she's more serious about it and she's not interested in
getting out of it. Now that's not so clear why. She could
also make a vow in a fit of anger anytime and try
to get out of it. So we'll talk about that later. תוספות
Tosafot doesn't like that answer. So basically תוספות's answer, which is sort
of completely absent in the גמרא, Gemara is that it's more tolerable
to have your food provided for you, you know, to be like
I don't know off sex for a week or have your food
provided for you through a third party for a week than it
is to forbid a certain type of a fruit upon yourself. I
don't understand why one is more tolerable than the other at all
and anyway the גמרא Gemara doesn't say it. Probably the best explanation
of how the גמרא Gemara answers because where's the answer to the
question? Why is this right away? Why don't we give this a
month? So it seems like the best answer, I think the ר"ן
Ran says this is
basically again this question of the interpersonal dynamics and what messages are
being sent. When he takes the vow, okay, people get angry, they
say things in anger, you give them time to cool off, so
we give it a month and she can sort of wait out
that month. Okay. But if
basically like she's making the vow and he's being מקיים mekayem it,
somehow it feels to her like, you know, I'm being angry and
you said good, you know, like go ahead, you know, stay angry
at me. I don't care. You know, and therefore that creates that
greater sense of emotional distance. And therefore that becomes therefore the reason
we say like okay, we gotta break you know this marriage has
got a problem we gotta move to a divorce. Again like why
we're so proactive in getting the divorce, you know, I mean the
only thing is that she can't eat kumquats, but okay, but at
least that explains a sense of like why it might be
more urgent or more severe. That's probably the best explanation of how
the גמרא's Gemara answering its question of why we don't give this
time according to שמואל. Shmuel. Yes?
When you say that הוא נותן אצבע בין שיניה hu nosein etzba
bein shineha has the sense of it's his fault and it's come
back to bite him? Oh.
רש"י Rashi suggests it, does he not, when he says שיניה והשיכה.
shineha vehishicha.
והשיך אותה. vehishich osa. He bit her, no?
Where is it?
שקיים
לה ונתן אצבע בין שיניה והשיכה.
she-kiyem la v'nosan
etzba bein shineha v'hishicha.
And she bit. No, it's...
I thought it meant והוא השיך אותה. vehu hishich osa. I thought
I read it with a מפיק ה mapik heh
but it's where his finger is.
between her teeth. Maybe, maybe סתם סתם.
stam stam. It's his fault and he comes back to bite and
then you give her the גט.
Get. Okay, that could be. That could be. Right. I got the
feeling. I got it earlier.
An earlier layer of pun because now if his finger's in her
mouth, now she can't eat. Oh, there you go. Okay. So let's
take a look. Anyway, so the question is, is the idea that
he's poking her, he's poking her in the
teeth, poking her in the eye or punching out her teeth, is
the idea that that just explains why he has to pay the
כתובה? Kesuvah? That's one problem. If she made the vow, why is
he paying the כתובה? Kesuvah? Or based on the last thing I
said, it's also explaining why we don't wait a month for them
to resolve it because she did it and he did this back
to her, so therefore this thing becomes less tolerable. Okay, so let's
take a look.
וסבר רבי מאיר v'savar Rabbi Meir who knows הנכפה בבין שיניה? hinkafa
b'vein sheineha? Really, Rabbi Meir would say that in this type of
a case she made the vow and he was מקיים mekayeim it,
he's to blame? והתניא v'hatanya we taught a ברייתא. Baraisa. האשה שנדרה
בנזיר, ha-ishah she-nadrah b'nazir,
a woman took a vow that she would be a נזיר. nazir.
ושמע בעלה ולא הפר לה, v'shama ba'alah v'lo hefer lah,
and the husband heard and he wasn't הפר meifer her. רבי מאיר
ורבי יהודה אומרים Rabbi Meir v'Rabbi Yehudah omrim היא נתנה אצבע בין
שיניה, hi nasnah etzba bein sheineha, she put her own finger in
her mouth between her teeth, she poked out her own eye. ולפיכך,
v'lifichach, אם רצה בעל להפר יפר, im ratzah ba'al l'hafer yafer,
while the husband could still be הפר meifer still the first day,
with twenty-four hours, then he could let him be הפר. meifer. ואם
אמר, v'im amar, but if he isn't הפר meifer and essentially you're
saying he wasn't הפר, meifer, and now after he wasn't הפר, meifer,
now she's a נזיר, nazir, then he says
אי אפשי באשה נדרנית, ee efshi b'ishah nadranis, I don't want a
vowing woman in my
house. She's always going to make things forbidden, there's always going to
be these obstacles and these problems, and now she's a נזירה nezirah
and all these things. So basically
he makes it her fault. I don't want such a woman. She
could always say it back: well, if you didn't want such a
woman, why didn't you annul my vows when you heard them? So
says that's not my, I don't care about that. You made the
vow. I don't like that and therefore so now you understand who's
to blame. But basically Rabbi Meir would say he's entitled to say
that. Yes, he could have annulled the vow, but he's entitled to
say that and put the blame on her.
תצא בלא כתובה teitzei b'lo kesuvah and she gets divorced without a
כתובה. Kesuvah. Now the question is do we insist they get divorced
or does that just mean if he chooses to divorce her he's
entitled not to give her the כתובה Kesuvah because he can make
it her fault? But clearly Rabbi Meir is saying if there's going
to be a divorce, there's not going to be a כתובה, Kesuvah,
he can lay the blame at her feet.
Come back to bite her.
Right. רבי יוסי ורבי אלעזר אומרים, Rabbi Yossi v'Rabbi Elazar omrim, no,
הוא נתן אצבע בין שיניה, hu nasan etzba bein sheineha, he was
the one that put the finger in her teeth. ולפיכך, v'lifichach, אם
רצה בעל להפר יפר. im ratzah ba'al l'hafer yafer. Yes, as long
as he wants to be הפר, meifer, he can be הפר, meifer,
as long as you have the time to do it. ואם אמר
אי אפשי באשה נדרנית v'im amar ee efshi b'ishah nadranis and if
after that time he basically says, I don't want such a woman
who makes these vows, okay, יוציא ויתן כתובה. yotzi v'yitein kesuvah. You
don't want such a woman? You should have annulled the vows. And
if you didn't, then it's your fault and therefore it's enough your
fault that if you want to divorce her, you'll have to pay
the כתובה. Kesuvah. So here we're talking about the primary question here
is not this type of a vow that makes it impossible for
them to stay married, I mean here it is because he's claiming
it does because he's saying that this vow is getting in the
way, but the key focus here is that when she makes a
vow and he is מקיים mekayeim it, does that mean that she
loses her כתובה Kesuvah payment? It's her fault, or does that mean
that he would still pay the כתובה? Kesuvah? It's enough his fault.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So there you have
Rabbi Meir saying it's her fault. So how could you read our
משנה, Mishnah. she made the vow and he was מקיים mekayeim it
and he has to pay the כתובה? Kesuvah? That's the case in
our משנה. Mishnah If Rabbi Meir says that he doesn't pay the
כתובה, Kesuvah, it's her fault. So the גמרא Gemara says איפכא, ipcha,
fine, let's reverse the names in the ברייתא. Baraisa. רבי מאיר ורבי
יהודה אומרים Rabbi Meir v'Rabbi Yehudah omrim הוא נתן, hu nasan, have
Rabbi Meir and Rabbi Yehudah being the ones that say it's his
fault and he would pay the כתובה, Kesuvah, and רבי יוסי ורבי
אלעזר אומרים Rabbi Yossi v'Rabbi Elazar omrim היא נתנה, hi nasnah, and
Rabbi Yossi and Rabbi Elazar being the ones that say it's her
fault. Okay, so it doesn't match up, so we'll switch around the
names. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, it's not going to work,
because
וסבר רבי יוסי היא נתנה? v'savar Rabbi Yossi hi nasnah? So Rabbi
Yossi would say it's her fault and therefore she doesn't get
a כתובה? Kesuvah? והתנן, v'hatnan, our משנה Mishnah about this thing about
the fruit, remember what the משנה Mishnah? goes on to say about
when it talks about the perfume? רבי יוסי אומר בעניות שלא נתן
קצבה, Rabbi Yossi omer b'aniyos shelo nasan kitzvah, if they're poor women,
it's only a problem if it's indefinite, and if it's rich women,
it's a month. Remember that from the משנה? Mishnah So you see
that Rabbi Yossi also feels that the law of the משנה Mishnah
would be in effect in these types of vows and he would
pay the כתובה. Kesuvah. So according to שמואל Shmuel that we set
up the whole משנה Mishna to be talking about she made the
vow and he was מקיים mekayeim it, so
you have the סתם משנה stam Mishnah which is presumably רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and רבי יוסי Rebi Yosi both accepting the premise and
saying. when there's a—they discuss how long will we wait, but they
basically say when there's a divorce he pays the כתובה. Ksuva. Right?
So you get that that we've made that משנה Mishna to be
this case and you have the סתם משנה stam Mishna which is
רבי מאיר Rebi Meir and רבי יוסי Rebi Yosi saying he'll pay
the כתובה, Ksuva, which basically means it's her fault. Okay? I mean
excuse me, it's his fault. It's his fault. Yeah, I was testing
you. It's his fault. So now we got a problem, because the
ברייתא Braita that the בית שמאי Beis Shammai faulted it is has
רבי מאיר Rebi Meir on one side of the debate and רבי
יוסי Rebi Yosi, on the other side of the debate, and our
משנה Mishna, has them both saying he pays the כתובה. Ksuva. So
the גמרא Gemara says: Okay, אימא, Eima, fine, let's just not switch
the names, you know, you have two on one side, two on
the other side, and we'll reverse them, let's actually mix up the
names. Okay? אימא Eima רבי מאיר ורבי יוסי אומרי Rebi Meir veRebi
Yosi omrei
fine, we'll have both רבי מאיר—we'll Rebi Meir take one from each,
רבי מאיר Rebi Meir and רבי יוסי Rebi Yosi now are the
ones that say הוא נותן, hu noten, he's the one to blame,
and רבי יהודה ורבי אלעזר אומרים היא נותנת, veRebi Yehuda veRebi Elazar
omrim hi notenet, Rebi Elazar and Rebi Yehuda says she's the one
to blame. Gemara says: That's still not gonna work, because we have
רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda who also says, according to the way we're
reading the משנה, Mishna that he's to blame. וסבר רבי יהודה היא
נותנת? Ve-savar Rebi Yehuda hi notenet? Rebi Yehuda says she's the one
to blame? והתנן, Ve-hatnan, our משנה Mishna, goes says, רבי יהודה אומר
בישראל, Rebi Yehuda omer be-Yisrael, and if it's this case about the
vow of the fruits, if he's a—if it's a non-כהן, Kohen, יום
אחד יקיים, yom echad yekayem, we wait one day. If it's a
כהן, Kohen, we wait two days. So basically again, he also buys
into the premise of the משנה, Mishna that there would be a
divorce and the husband would pay the כתובה. Ksuva. So in our
משנה Mishna you got the סתם משנה stam Mishna which is רבי
מאיר, Rebi Meir, you got רבי יהודה, Rebi Yehuda, you got רבי
יוסי, Rebi Yosi you got all these guys in the משנה Mishna,
that are all saying that divorce and pay the כתובה. Ksuva. And
the way we explained it according to שמואל Shmuel is she made
the vow, he was מקיים, mikayem, so all of them are saying
in that case he's to blame. But in the ברייתא Braita we
actually have two of them saying he's to blame and two not.
So we have three in the משנה, Mishna you're not gonna solve
the problem. So the גמרא Gemara says... okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says... where was it...
אימא, Eima, fine, we'll have it as both two against two, we'll
have it three against one in the ברייתא, Braita, we'll completely rewrite
the ברייתא. Braita. רבי מאיר ורבי יהודה ורבי יוסי אומרים הוא נותן.
Rebi Meir veRebi Yehuda veRebi Yosi omrim hu noten. Fine, Rebi Meir,
Rebi Yehuda, and Rebi Yosi all saying הוא נותן, hu noten, he's
to blame. ורבי אלעזר ורבי אלעזר veRebi Elazar veRebi Elazar will be
the sole person—instead of two against two it's three against one—אומר היא
נותנת, omer hi notenet, she's to blame. Now the גמרא Gemara sort
of realizes at this stage it's a little absurd, because it's one
thing to say it was two against two and it got a
little—we got a little bit confused which two were on which side,
but to say it was three against one, right, the משנה Mishna,
would not have been written as a two against two if there
really was a debate of three against one. So now the גמרא
Gemara says there's another explanation, which is not that much more satisfactory,
but okay. It says: ואם תמצי לומר זוגי זוגי קתני, Ve-im timtzi
lomar zugi zugi katani, and if you insist on saying that the
ברייתא Braita was written two against two and we can't sort of
disrupt that, so nevertheless I'll tell you: אימא Eima רבי מאיר ורבי
אלעזר אומרים היא נותנת, Rebi Meir veRebi Elazar omrim hi notenet, Rebi
Meir and Rebi Elazar will say she's to blame, רבי יהודה ורבי
יוסי אומרים הוא נותן, Rebi Yehuda veRebi Yosi omrim hu noten, Rebi
Yehuda and Rebi Yosi, their names are mentioned explicitly in our משנה,
Mishna it says הוא נותן, hu noten, he's to blame. So okay,
so we have רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda and רבי יוסי Rebi Yosi
that are mentioned explicitly in our משנה Mishna and therefore they'll be
the ones that say הוא נותן, hu noten, he's to blame. But
the other reason we thought the משנה Mishna was going like רבי
מאיר Rebi Meir is we assumed סתם משנה stam Mishna was רבי
מאיר. Rebi Meir. גמרא Gemara. says: Okay, that we can play with.
רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi say הוא נותן,
hu noten, he's to blame, רבי מאיר Rebi Meir and רבי אלעזר
Rebi Elazar says היא נותנת, hi notenet, she's to blame, וסתמא דלא
כרבי מאיר, ve-stama de-lo ke-Rebi Meir, and this סתם משנה stam Mishna
would not be going like רבי מאיר. Rebi Meir. Okay, so we
did a lot of juggling. So according to שמואל, Shmuel, in order
to explain why we're more strict about the case of fruit, because
רב Rav could just say it was a case of סתם. stam.
But according to שמואל Shmuel we make it this special case, she
made the vow, he was מקיים, mikayem, we get the whole discussion
in those cases who's to blame, okay, and therefore we have to
then make our משנה Mishna. fit with another pre-existing debate of two
תנאים Tannaim against two תנאים Tannaim about who's to blame in those
cases. Fine. Now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, וסבר רבי יוסי בעניות שלא נתן קצבה? Ve-savar Rebi Yosi be-aniyot
she-lo natan kitzva? Now Rebi Yosi holds that by the poor women,
if it's an indefinite vow, it's—only would be a problem of not
having certain perfumes or whatever if it's indefinite. If it's a—if it's
a limited period of time, poor women often go a long—a reasonable
period of time without having, you know, perfume and whatever. So does
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi really hold that by poor women it's—if there's
no limit then they get divorced? אלמא בעל מצי מפר. Alma ba'al
matzi mefer. So the implicit part about that is if we set
up this dynamic according to שמואל, Shmuel, she makes the vow and
he was מקיים mikayem it, that he was in a position to
annul it, right? That's the whole way we explain this משנה. Mishna,
So now we have to say one minute, why is he in
a position to annul the vow? Meaning we have two problems with
these vows. One is why is the vow getting between their marriage
and how does getting divorced help? We already discussed that. But the
other question we have is, according to שמואל Shmuel that he reads
the משנה, Mishna. she made the vow and he was מקיים, mikayem,
means that it was a type of vow he could have annulled.
So is this a type of vow he can annul? So what
you have to know is that there are two types of vows
that the husband can annul. The תורה Torah says, it says if
a woman takes a vow לענות נפש, le-anot nefesh, אישה יקימנו ואישה
יפירנו. ishah yekimenu ve-ishah yeferenu.
If the woman takes a vow to afflict herself, the husband can
establish it or the husband can... can annul it. So that's a
vow of עינוי נפש. innuy nefesh. So we have to determine what
type of vow is considered an affliction. Okay, now you would say,
okay, maybe anything that's about a denial, self-denial of pleasure is לענות
נפש. l'annot nefesh. So here it's not perfume, alright, so fine, we'll
talk about it. So it's perfume and it's fruit and it's this
and it's that. Maybe so, okay, the husband could annul it. That's
one category. The other category which is not as explicit in the
תורה is it says right בין איש לאשתו. bein ish l'ishto.
That says these are the laws between husband and wife. So the
גמרא Gemara says anything that relates, that affects, gets in the way
of their relationship, that's בין איש לאשתו, bein ish l'ishto, that also
he can annul even if it's not about עינוי נפש. innuy nefesh.
Okay, so we won't sort of explain what type of things fall
into that category, but that's a separate category. Now the difference between
which category you put something in is, is it that it's considered
עינוי נפש, innuy nefesh, then his annulment works for everybody. Let's say
she basically says, right, you know, I won't get, you know, any,
you know, all people's in the world's fruit is forbidden to me,
okay, and he annuls it. So she can get benefit from everybody's
fruit. Let's say he, wait a minute, let's say we sort of
said that no, that category was not considered to be עינוי נפש,
innuy nefesh, that was just considered to be something that got in
the way of the two of them. Then when he annuls it,
it would only remove her getting benefit from his fruit. It wouldn't
remove it from she would still be forbidden against other people's. So
if we consider it עינוי נפש, innuy nefesh, his annulment works across
the board. If we consider it just something that is that interfered
with their relationship, his annulment only works for the degree that it's
to remove that barrier between them, not for other aspects. Yes.
What does annulment entail?
What does he have to say? He just has to say מופר
לך. mufar lach. That's it. Yeah, right, exactly.
But we're not talking about any of these other things, like you
know, he said, okay, I'm going to give five hundred dollars to
צדקה tzedakah today.
No, no, no. We're talking about specific איסורים. issurim. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. So we have רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi in our משנה. Mishna, Now the way we set up the
משנה, Mishna, she took the vow and he annulled this, which means
that according to שמואל, Shmuel, that's how we're reading our משנה, Mishna
which means that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi would say that I mean
he was מקיים mekayem it, but which means that רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi would say he's in a position to annul it. So the
גמרא Gemara... says
is that really true? ורמינהו, u'reminhu, I'll ask you, we got a
משנה Mishna. in נדרים that says the following, that says אלו דברים
שהבעל מפר, eilu devarim she'haba'al meifer,
the following are things that the husband can annul, דברים שיש בהם
עינוי נפש, devarim sheyeish bahem innuy nefesh, things that are a affliction
of the soul of the person, right? So אם ארחץ אם לא
ארחץ, im erchatz im lo erchatz, if she makes a vow about
bathing or not bathing, I'm not going to sort of unpack exactly
why one's in the positive and negative but basically a type of
a vow that would prevent her from bathing. אם אתקשט אם לא
אתקשט im etkashet im lo etkashet
or a type of vow that would prevent her from wearing jewelry.
By the way, I should say that the husband can not only
annul vows, he can also annul a שבועה, shevuah, an oath. So
whether it's saying a שבועה shevuah that I won't wear jewelry or
whether it's saying all jewelry in the world is forbidden to me,
either one of those would be something he can annul. אמר רבי
יוסי אין אלו נדרי עינוי נפש. amar Rabbi Yossi ein eilu nidrei
innuy nefesh.
That's not enough. There's a threshold. That's not enough of an affliction.
It's quite fascinating, tells you something about their society that not bathing
is not considered an affliction and that's like indefinitely not bathing. ואלו
הן נדרי עינוי נפש. v'eilu hein nidrei innuy nefesh. You know what
you need to do to be considered עינוי נפש? innuy nefesh? שלא
אוכל בשר, shelo ochel basar,
not to eat meat. That's real affliction. So funny, tells that to
everybody who's a vegetarian. ושלא אשתה יין v'shelo eshteh yayin or not
to drink wine.
ושלא אתקשט v'shelo etkashet and
that I would not adorn myself not just in general but specifically
בבגדי צבעונים bebigdei tzevonim and
in colored clothing. So I don't ask me why these, if anything,
I would have said that those are much less עינוי נפש innuy
nefesh than the things the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said. But without
getting into that, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi does not consider to be
the
issues about jewelry or perfume to be עינוי נפש. innuy nefesh. So
that's the case in our משנה. Mishna The case in the משנה
Mishnah is she was forbidding a certain type of jewelry or perfume
on herself, right? So why did רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi implicitly say
he could be מיפר? meifer? If here רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is
saying he's not in a position to be מיפר. meifer. Right? Everybody
understand the question? Okay, so the גמרא says like
this, it
says הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, okay, so even though it's
not עינוי נפש innuy nefesh for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose not to
wear certain perfumes, here what we're talking about בדברים שבינו לבינה. bidvarim
shebeino l'veina. It's a type of, yes, it's true it's not in
the עינוי נפש innuy nefesh category, but it's still is in the
בינו לבינה beino l'veina category. And since it's in the בינו לבינה
beino l'veina category, that's why he can still annul it because it's
still basically when she's not doing that, as I said, it matters
which category you put it in. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose. is
just saying it's not in this עינוי נפש innuy nefesh where his
annulment will work for everybody. It's just in the בינו לבינה beino
l'veina that the annulment will only work for the two, you know,
for the aspect that relates to the two of them. Okay.
Could it be it's both, right? Could be it's a subjective way
of understanding עינוי נפש innuy nefesh in this relationship.
Yeah,
I mean, but the question is you have to... Yeah, but the
question is you can have things that are בינו לבינה beino l'veinah
that you would never define as possibly, that you wouldn't define as
עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh. Yeah. Okay, but anyway so the answer is
that he says, you know what, you're right, it's not עינוי נפש,
inuy nefesh, but that just means it doesn't mean he can't annul
it, it just means it's not in that category which is a
which is a more powerful category of his annulment, but it still
is in the בינו לבינה beino l'veinah category and that's why he
could annul it. So the גמרא says הני למאן דאמר דברים שבינו
לבינה הבעל מפר, hani l'man d'amar dvarim shebeino l'veinah habaal meifer, that's
good if you say that the husband can annul things that are
between them. אלא למאן דאמר אין הבעל מפר מאי איכא למימר, ela
l'man d'amar ein habaal meifer mai ika l'meimar, but if the husband
can't annul it, what can you say? Now, where was this debated?
דאיתמר, d'itmar, it was taught, דברים שבינו לבינה, dvarim shebeino l'veinah, things
that are between the two of them that are presumably not עינוי
נפש. inuy nefesh. רב הונא אמר הבעל מפר, Rav Huna amar habaal
meifer, the husband can annul
it, רב אדא בר אהבה אמר אין הבעל מפר, Rav Adda bar
Abba amar ein habaal meifer, שלא מצינו שועל שמת בעפר פיר. shelo
matzinu shual shemet b'afar pir. We've never found that a fox will
die in the dust in which it was in which it sort
of grew up in, in which it was so meaning if there's
a thing that is not real עינוי נפש inuy nefesh and it's
still and it's there but it's standing between the two of them,
they'll be able to manage, like, you know, this is sort of
within their domestic relationship and it's not this big עינוי נפש. inuy
nefesh. It's not some type of a thing that's really seen as
enough of a problem that they can't somehow negotiate it and manage.
It won't kill you.
Now, תוספות says there is no debate whether a husband can annul
דברים שבינו לבינה. dvarim shebeino l'veinah. That is taken as like axiomatic
in the גמרא. That's not what they're debating. What they're debating is
when רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says these small things are not עינוי
נפש, inuy nefesh, did he mean to say the husband can't annul
them at all, or did he mean to say they're not עינוי
נפש inuy nefesh but they're still in the בינו לבינה beino l'veinah
category? So it's a question within רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose Everybody agrees
in principle the husband can annul בינו לבינה. beino l'veinah. But when
רבי יוסי sort of downgraded these things about bathing and perfume and
jewelry, was he basically saying this is all trivial, it's not עינוי
נפש, inuy nefesh, it's not even important enough that the husband can
annul it, this is not a legitimate problem, okay, and is that
what he was saying? You'll manage. Or was he saying no, it's
not in the עינוי נפש inuy nefesh category but it is in
the בינו לבינה. beino l'veinah. So if you say that according to
רבי יוסי it's so trivial that it's not even בינו לבינה beino
l'veinah and the husband can't annul it, we're back to our problem.
Why does our משנה Mishnah the way שמואל's Shmuel reading the משנה
Mishnah assume that the husband was in a position to annul it?
So the גמרא says like
this: אלא הכא במאי עסקינן, ela hacha b'mai askinan, what are we
talking about? כגון דתלינהו לקישוטיה בתשמיש המטה, k'gon d'talinhu l'kishuteha b'tashmish hamitah,
like I told you earlier, like we would have read the משנה
mishna. according to רב. Rav. It's not about the jewelry per se
or the perfume per se, it's about sex and the perfume is
the trigger, is like the condition. What does that mean?
She says the following:
יאסר הנאת תשמישך עלי, ye'aser hana'at tashmishcha alai,
the benefit of having sex with you will be forbidden to me,
אם אתקשט, im etkashat, if I put on jewelry. So therefore effectively
the jewelry is forbidden. But now we also understand why they need
to get divorced because what we're concerned about is that the sex
will be forbidden, okay? And now we also understand why the husband
can annul it. He can annul it because ultimately the vow, not
the condition, but the vow forbids the sex and that actually is
עינוי נפש inuy nefesh and בינו לבינה. beino l'veinah. Okay, כדאמר רב
כהנא, k'd'amar Rav Kahana, like רב כהנא Rav Kahana says, דאמר רב
כהנא הנאת תשמישי עליך, d'amar Rav Kahana hana'at tashmishi alecha,
if the wife says the pleasure of my sex is forbidden to
you, כופה ומשמשתו, kofeh u'm'shameshto, you force her to have sex with
him. I mean it doesn't literally mean you beat her up, but
anyway the vow isn't binding because he has a right to have
sex with her and she's trying to forbid that thing to him
that he's entitled to. But if she says הנאת תשמישך עלי, hana'at
tashmishcha alai, she does this indirect way, no, I'm not forbidding the
pleasure of my sex on you, I don't have a right to
forbid it on you, but I'm forbidding the pleasure of your sex
on me, okay? So either way it winds up preventing them from
having sex and in that case the vow is binding if the
woman says that. יפר, yeifer, he should and he needs to annul
it because the vow would be binding otherwise. And why does he
have to annul it? ומשום שאין מאכילין לאדם דבר האסור לו, u'mishum
she'ein maachilin l'adam davar ha'asur lo, because if he doesn't annul it
then you'd be in a position where it would be forbidden to
have sex, so either they'd be having sex and they'd be transgressing
or they wouldn't be having sex, either of those is not acceptable,
so in that case he has to annul it. Okay, so now
how is this relevant to רב כהנא? Rav Kahana? So now the
גמרא says like this, I'm sorry, okay, fine, no, no, no, I'm
sorry,
so that is the statement of רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. So you
see from רב כהנא Rav Kahana that, I mean it's not exactly
clear why it quoted רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, but basically it's because
רב כהנא Rav Kahana says if there's a vow there that's going
to get in the way of sex,
he obviously can annul. So it was a way of bringing in
רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. But basically the point was that the jewelry
was a condition, the vow was about sex, that's why the husband
is in a position to annul it and that's why if he
doesn't annul it obviously they're going to have to get divorced. So
now the גמרא says one minute, the גמרא...
Why do they have to get divorced right away? So the Gemara
says like this: ולא תתקשט ולא תיאסר, v'lo tishkashe v'lo teasor,
okay
but there'll be a problem if she puts on the jewelry. But
if she doesn't, they'll never be forbidden. So why you know why
is it you know why why is this the problem? Let's just
manage this situation. Exactly. So the Gemara says no, אם כן קרו
לה מנוולת. im ken karu lah menuvela.
No, because then people will tell her, you know, you're disgusting, you
never put on perfume, or whatever meaning so what let them call
her that. So the way sort of Rashi says it is she'll
be pressured to it's not sustainable. Not viable. We think that she's
not we sort of see it's inevitable or there's enough of a
real concern that we're going to we have to look at that
as the what we're expecting to happen. And therefore there is a
problem here with them having sex. And therefore that's why we have
to push for resolving it or a divorce. So the Gemara says
okay, but why immediately? ותתקשט ותיאסר? v'tishkashe v'teasor? Even if she becomes
forbidden,
אילו בית שמאי שתי שבתות ואילו בית הלל שבת אחת, ilu Beis
Shammai shte shabsos v'ilu Beis Hillel shabbos achas, right? And so
according to Shmuel, even when the vow takes effect, you've got a
week or two weeks to figure it out to to see if
you could work it out. So if this is how we're explaining
the ברייתא braisa with Shmuel that it's about a vow of sex,
why is it immediate? It's not really the vow of פירות, peiros,
it's really the vow of sex. So the Gemara says no, הני
מילי היכא דאדרה איהו. hani milei heicha de'adrah ihu.
That's when he took the vow. דסברה desavrah
because she says he made the sex forbidden because she figures מירתח
רתח עלי, mirtach rasach alai,
he's just getting angry at me. ואתי מיתבא דעתיה, v'asi meisva datei,
he'll come down, we'll give it a week, we'll give it two
weeks, he'll come down, he'll find a פתח, pesach, we'll get out
of it. That's tolerable for a week or two. אבל הכא דנדרה
איהי, aval hacha denadrah ihi,
here where she was the one who did it, ושתק לה, v'shasak
lah, and he was okay with it. Now also remember, it's not
about it's not about perfume or food, it's about sex. She took
a vow about not having sex and he's the one that said
fine, I'll be מקיים mekayeim that. So he was calm. Right? He
wasn't angry. He was the one that was calm and he was
being מקיים mekayeim this vow that was going to get sex make
sex forbidden. So סברה מדאשתיק, savrah mid'ishtik, he was quiet, מיסנא הוא
דסני לי, misna hu desani li, he must hate me. So therefore
it's a very different dynamic and therefore it creates even a bigger
sort of a obstacle between them and we demand a sooner divorce.
So bottom line is the way the Gemara explained it according to
Shmuel and it would certainly explain it according to Rav. Rav would
have him making the vow and Shmuel has her making the vow
and him being מקיים mekayeim it. But in the end we made
it not about the fruit or the perfume but we made it
about the sex. And that's why they're going to have to get
divorced and that's why because according to Shmuel that he was מקיים
mekayeim it, it was more urgent because it was seen as like
he's calm and he's okay with it and therefore we
don't
give it a month.
Alright once you say okay fine.
Fine, whatever. I understand, what can I tell you? Yes, yes. Anyway
but that's the logic about why we don't give it a month,
we do it right away. But according to Rav, the reason we
do it right away is because you didn't explicitly say the time
limit in the vow. Yes.
עינוי נפש inui nefesh only mean her suffering or could it also
mean she's caught in a struggle?
No, it's her. It's about hers. Yes. So now the Gemara says
like this: Let's just get to the משנה. רבי יוסי אומר בעניות
שלא נתן קצבה. Rabbi Yosei omer be'aniyos shelo nasan kitzvah. But this
perfume case, it's for poor women, it's only intolerable if it's indefinite.
So the Gemara says really? Only indefinite? What if it's 20 years?
Would that be okay? So the Gemara says וכמה קצבה. v'chamah kitzvah.
But you know, what would be the limit? Meaning, you know, so
meaning, you know, at what stage would it be considered to be,
you know,
beyond limitless even though it is a limit? Right? Even though there's
a limit. So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל י"ב חודש. amar Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel yud beis chodesh. Up until 12 months is tolerable.
More than a year's not tolerable. That's considered to be without a
limit. רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן עשר שנים. Rabbah bar
bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan eser shanim. 10 years. How'd we get
to that? I have no idea.
רב חסדא אמר אבימי רגל. Rav Chisda amar Avimi regel. Without a
limit means up until the next רגל. regel. But wait, less than
a... yeah well we'll take a look. שכן בנות ישראל מתקשטות ברגל.
sheken benos Yisrael miskashetos baregel. To say that they can't go ahead
and put on some nice jewelry or the way Rashi read it
nice perfume on יום טוב, Yom Tov,
that's intolerable even for the poor women. Alright, so that's a nice
reinterpretation of the word without limit. Last two lines, פשיטא ל-30 יום.
peshita l-shloshim yom. מאי שנא ל-30 יום? mai shna l-shloshim yom? Why
do rich women 30 days is intolerable? אמר אביי שכן אשה חשובה
נהנית מריח קישוטיה ל-30 יום. amar Abaye sheken isha chashuvah nehenes meriach
kishuteiha l'shloshim yom. So here the Gemara makes it clear we're talking
about perfume, that she still has some of the residual aroma of
the perfume. I guess if you're not bathing too often, that's possible
for up until 30 days. More than that it's not tolerable. Oh
you understand? No, it's only day 30. Alright.
Rabbi Linzer? Yes. The statement... the רב כהנא Rav Kahana statement...